<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Comparing Perspectives</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ly_er">Lyette Erin</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                    <name xml:id="br_he">Brooke Herron</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Description of project</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <surface>
            <graphic url="w_brown.jpeg"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="main">Comparing Perspectives</head>
                <byline>Examining the Rhetoric of a prominent white Newspaper Differed from a prominent Black Newspaper in their reporting of the lynching of Will Brown</byline>
                <p>Following the reconstruction of 1910s, thousands of African Americans were recruited to come work as strikebreakers at the meatpacking plants located in Omaha, Nebraska. By the 1920s, the number of African Americans doubled to over 10,000 which was the second-highest concentration of blacks in America at the time. This created a great social divide in the community, where the working-class whites were showing great hostility towards blacks. As tensions between white and black workers in the stockyards were festering, on September 25, 1919, 19-year-old Agnes Loebeck reported that she had been raped. Local media reports were quick to report and broadcast this disturbing allegation, and one day later Will Brown was arrested by police and later identified by Loebeck. This series of events is what ultimately led to the unforgettable Omaha Race Riot and public lynching of Will Brown.</p>
            <lb></lb>
                <p>The purpose of this site is to demonstrate the two different media portrayals of the events that took place in front of the Douglas County Courthouse in downtown Omaha on September 28th and 29th. The first newspaper that will be examined is The Omaha Monitor which was famously known for being devoted to the interests of colored Americans and was the most widely read of all African American newspapers in Omaha during that time. To compare this rhetoric that was mainly curated towards blacks, publications from the Omaha World-Herald will be further analyzed, as this daily newspaper was run by predominantly white editors and publishers. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
    </TEI>